A more appropriate measure in this case, might be the median.
قد يكون الوسيط مقياسًا أكثر ملاءمةً في هذه الحالة.
The median is a value that divides our data set such that
فالوسيط هو قيمة تقسم مجموعة البيانات على أن يكون
50% of the values are larger while the remaining 50% are smaller.
50% من القيم أكبر بينما الـ 50% المتبقية أصغر.
For our data set,
بالنسبة لمجموعة البيانات،
we have a median of eight.
لدينا وسيط يساوي ثمانية.
This is a much better response than the 12 and a half dogs reported by the mean.
وهذه إجابة أفضل كثيرًا من 12 كلبًا ونصف التي يدل عليها الوسيط.
Not only does eight sit in the middle of our data set,
ولا يقتصر الأمر على وجود ثمانية في منتصف مجموعة البيانات،
but it doesn't split any of our dogs in half.
ولكنها لا تقسم أيًا من كلابنا نصفين.
As a note on calculating the median,
وكملحوظة بخصوص حساب الوسيط،
the actual calculation of the median depends on whether we're working with
يعتمد الحساب الفعلي للوسيط على سواء أكنا نتعامل
a data set with an even number of values or an odd number of values.
مع مجموعة بيانات بها عدد زوجي للبيانات أو عدد فردي للبيانات.
Let's consider a couple of examples to illustrate this point.
لنفكر في مثالين لتوضيح هذه النقطة.
The first thing we should do is order the values from smallest to largest.
وأول ما علينا فعله هو ترتيب هذه القيم من الأصغر إلى الأكبر.
In this top case,
في هذه الحالة العليا،
we are working with seven values.
نتعامل مع سبع قيم.
In notation we might say, n equals seven.
في المنهج يمكننا أن نقول n تساوي سبعة.
Because this is an odd number,
ولأن هذا عدد فردي،
we have the median as the exact middle value,
فالوسيط يكون تمامًا مثل القيمة المتوسطة،
in this case, the number three.
وفي هذه الحالة، يكون العدد ثلاثة.
In a second case,
وفي حالة ثانية،
let's consider n to be an even value.
لنعتبر أن n تساوي عددًا زوجيًا.
Let's find the median of the following list.
لنجد الوسيط للقائمة التالية.
Again, we should first put these values in order.
ومرة أخرى، يجب علينا أولاً ترتيب هذه القيم.
Because there isn't an exact center value, we will,
نظرًا لعدم وجود قيمة مركزية دقيقة،
in this case,take the mean of the two values in the center as our median.
سنأخذ في هذه الحالة متوسط القيمتين في المركز على أنهما الوسيط.
Notice, this does not even need to be a number in our data set.
لاحظوا، أن هذا لا يتطلب حتى أن يكون عددًا في مجموعة البيانات لدينا.
Because n is equal to eight for this example,
نظرًا لأن n تساوي ثمانية في هذا المثال،
the mean of the fourth and
فإن متوسط القيمتين الرابعة
the fifth values will provide to us the median for this data set.
والخامسة يوضح لنا الوسيط لمجموعة البيانات هذه.
Moving four values from each of the sides,
ومن خلال نقل أربع قيم من الجانبين،
makes it so that we take the mean of three and five to obtain the median of four.
يمكننا أخذ المتوسط من بين ثلاثة وخمسة للحصول على وسيط أربعة.